Good morning, today's דף daf is י"ז, yud-zayin, and the גמרא Gemara
is in the middle of trying to figure out a contradiction between
מידות Middot and תמיד Tamid in terms of where the various rooms
of the בית המוקד Beit HaMoked were situated or how they were
used, and the only reason it's discussing this is because it follows
a sort of structure that the גמרא Gemara also showed a contradiction
between יומא Yoma and תמיד Tamid in terms of the order of
the lighting of the נרות nerot and the burning of the קטורת,
ketoret, and it said there was a different author to the author
of the סתם משניות stam Mishnayot of תמיד Tamid as opposed to
the סתם משניות stam Mishnayot of יומא. Yoma. So here it's doing
the same with מידות Middot and תמיד Tamid and showed a contradiction
about in this בית המוקד, Beit HaMoked, in this large chamber, that
there were four corner rooms, which one of them was used for
the sheep for the קרבן תמיד, korban tamid, and there's a contradiction,
and the basic answer was also a different author, that the author
of מידות Middot was רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov.
Okay, and that's where we were up to now, and so I
guess we'll pick up with this first line of י"ז עמוד א':
yud-zayin amud aleph: אלא שמע מינה רבי אליעזר בן יעקב היא שמע
מינה. Ella shema mina Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hi shema mina. So
at the end of a long discussion yesterday, the conclusion was you
see that the author of מידות Middot is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov and has a different opinion than the author
of תמיד Tamid in terms of how those rooms were used. רבא
בריה דרב יצחק אמר האי לשכה אקצויי מקציא. Rava brei deRav Yitzchak
amar hai lishka akzoiye makzeia. Now what you have to remember is
that the contradiction was that in one of them
in תמיד Tamid it said that it was
the northwestern chamber was used for the sheep and in מידות
Middot it said the southwestern chamber.
So just to remind us, I've got ourselves
markers so I'll use them. Okay so here's your בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, okay this is north,
and
this is south. Okay let's say this is עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim
which has its own four chambers which
we discussed yesterday that's שער ניקנור Shaar Nicanor and this is the
עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. Okay here's the מזבח,
mizbeach,
here's the אולם, ulam, the היכל. heichal. Okay there's your בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Okay so there was a room that was in the
north and this was called בית המוקד, Beit HaMoked, let's say they
had a big fire to keep everybody warm. תוספות Tosafot actually says
one of the reasons of the fire was to use extra wood
to go on the מזבח mizbeach and it had these four chambers.
So our thing in תמיד Tamid said that it was the... so
the משנה mishna in תמיד Tamid said that it was the... what
was it? לשכת טלאים הייתה במקצוע צפונית מערבית. Lishkat telaim hayta b'miktzoa
tzafonit maaravit. The northwest. So the משנה mishna in תמיד Tamid said
that this was the one for the for the sheep for
the קרבן תמיד, korban tamid, that was the משנה mishna in תמיד
Tamid said that, and the משנה mishna in מידות Middot said that
it was the southwest. Okay this is the משנה mishna in מידות
Middot said that, that was the contradiction. Which room was it? And
as Rivka pointed out, it's interesting that according to מידות Middot it
was actually in the עזרה azarah in the קודש kodesh where they
would have all these sheep so now so that's quite fascinating. Okay.
Is it vocalized בית המוקד Beit HaMoked or בית המוקד? Beit HaMokad?
Probably מוקד. moked. Did I say מוקד? mokad?
No I said מוקד. moked.
It's not מוקד? moked?
No it's מוקד. mokad.
Isn't מוקד mokad סמיכות? smikhut?
No.
I don't know.
Okay. The grammarians can figure that out.
Does it make
a difference which it is or is it just historical accuracy? It
doesn't make a difference. Yeah it does not really make a difference,
it's just historical accuracy and it's just you know to deal with
the fact of how come there's a contradiction in the describes, it's
a basis of yeah it's just
it's not about הלכה.
halakha. I mean one of the amongst one of these discussions earlier
תוספות Tosafot said, you know how come the גמרא Gemara sometimes asks
הלכתא למשיחא, hilkhata limshicha, like what do I care this is just
a messianic הלכה halakha and sometimes it's not concerned about that and
תוספות Tosafot says yeah like you know not only sometimes the גמרא
Gemara you know sort of raises that issue. This isn't even a
הלכה halakha let alone הלכתא למשיחא. hilkhata limshicha. This is just a
question about how was it used? But you know you got a
whole מסכת מידות masechet Middot that's about history and not really about
הלכה. halakha. But right so the only reason we're discussing it here
is just to deal with this conundrum of this contradiction, so thank
you. So here's the so let's take a look at the next
answer. רבא בריה דרב יצחק אמר האי לשכה אקצויי מקציא, Rava brei
deRav Yitzchak amar hai lishka akzoiye makzeia, this לשכה. lishka. לשכה *lishka*
was basically like רש"י *Rashi* sort of says it was sort of
like designated, אקצויי *aktzuyei* could mean designated, but רש"י *Rashi* also says
it sort of means it was like extended. דאתי מצפון מתחזי ליה
בדרום ודאתי מדרום מתחזי ליה בצפון *de'ati mitzafon mitchazi lei bedarom v'de'ati
midarom mitchazi lei
betzafon*. When you came from the north, it looked like it was
in the south, and when you came from the south, it looked
like it was in the north.
So basically what תוספות *Tosafot* says here is that here's an answer
to your problem, is
that it's not that there was a debate where it was. Is
that actually, okay, here's your chamber, okay? Okay, let me just pull
it out of the large picture. And as opposed to saying it
was a debate whether it was here or here, right, whether it
was, this would be what, this is northwest, this is northwest,
okay, whether it's in the northwest or the southwest, it basically was
sort of like both, okay? It was like a room that was
sort of like that. So are you going to describe that room,
I don't know why you don't just describe it in the west,
okay, but the difference was, are you describing it in the northwest
or the southwest, because somehow if you're coming from the south, okay,
just standing here, it looks to you like oh, it's off to
the north. And if you're just standing here in the north, it
looks to you like oh, it's off to the south. Maybe it's
too big so you don't, so you've got that sense. Imagine it
was sort of like right around there. Okay, so that basically it
was neither the northwest or the southwest, it was a question of
perspective, okay, which is not a very fascinating answer, and why the
משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* didn't just say it's in the west and the
middle of the west, okay, but that's a basic answer. This room
was sort of like midpoint between the two, so for somebody standing
in the south, they looked at it and it's not near them,
they see it way off there, it looks to them it's in
the northwest, especially if you imagine if you're like I don't know
standing here or something. Anyway, so you know you just see like
oh over there there's a room, it's in the northwest and this
way it looks like it's in the southwest and that's why you
have the different versions. All right, yes.
That could be a naive question, but could it be a מחלוקת
*machloket* between two משניות *Mishnayot* about the מידות Middot, *midot* of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* pre-חורבן *Churban*? In other words, shouldn't
they have eyewitness accounts?
Yeah, well first of all there's a question about whether these, well
no who's writing, what makes you say they were being written pre-חורבן
*Churban*? You know they were being post. Somebody told me that this
issue came up the other day at the דף *daf* in the
RJC. Were you telling me this, Noam? Who was it? No, maybe
Jonathan was telling it to me. Anyway, that they were saying like
how could you forget? They said, okay look, we just redid a
reconstruction here ten years ago, who remembers what this you know where
we did this, what this chamber was used for? It was a
big מחלוקת *machloket*. Nobody could get it, nobody could agree on those
things.
So the reality is, yeah you could forget. But anyway, so all
right.
ומיסתברא דממערב דרומא הוי *u'mistabra de'mimareiv droma havei*.
Now
that it makes sense that it was more to the southwest. Why
does it make sense it was more to the southwest? ממאי mi-mai?
*Mimai*? What makes you say that? מדרימינא לחם הפנים lechem hapanim אלחם
הפנים ומשנינן u-mishaninan, אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע amar Rav Huna
brei de-Rav Yehoshua, מר כחשיב דרך ימין mar kachashiv derech yamin, ומר
כחשיב דרך שמאל u-mar kachashiv derech smol, *mideramina Lechem HaPanim a'Lechem HaPanim
u'meshaninan amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua mar kachashiv derech yamin umar
kachashiv derech smol*. Here's why. Because there's another contradiction between תמיד Tamid.
*Tamid* and מידות Middot *Middot*.
What is the contradiction? Because the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* in תמיד Tamid
*Tamid* says the following. Okay, the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* in תמיד Tamid.
*Tamid* said that this was for sheep. And then it kept on
going around and telling you what the other things were used for.
So if you remember, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* in תמיד Tamid *Tamid*
said that the first one was used for sheep and then it
said and then it listed them. And then one was used for
the seals, חותמות *chotamot*. Now we're going to assume because in all
things we go counterclockwise, the standard. So we're going to assume we're
going to go counterclockwise. It said one was used for the seals,
okay, not our seals, the other type of seals. One was used
for the seals, one was used for בית המוקד Beit HaMoked. *Beit
HaMoked*, another place where they had a fire, and one was the
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim *Lechem HaPanim*. So if we're going around, this
would be בית המוקד *Beit HaMoked*
and this would be לחם הפנים lechem hapanim? *Lechem HaPanim*. That was
the
משנה *Mishnah* in מידות Middot *Middot*, okay, in תמיד Tamid *Tamid*. Now
the משנה *Mishnah* in מידות Middot, *Middot* however said differently. The משנה
*Mishnah* in
מידות Middot
*Middot* said the following.
Okay, so the south, it said the southwest was the טלאים *tlayim*,
so that's contradiction number one because it said the southwest was the
sheep. Okay, so already we have a contradiction, the south and that
was what we've been focusing on. And then it said the southeast
was לחם הפנים lechem hapanim. *Lechem HaPanim*, so again going in this
type of a counterclockwise circle, it said this was the לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim. *Lechem HaPanim*.
So that's contradiction number two. Okay, and then it said מזרח צפונית
*mizrach tzafonit*, this was where the בית חשמונאי *Beit Chashmonai* had the
אבני מזבח avnei mizbeach *avnei mizbei'ach*, a little...
Chashmonai had the אבני מזבח, Mizbeach the stones that were defiled by
the Greeks. And the fourth one was where you went down to
בית הטבילה. Beit HaTevilah. There were steps getting you down to בית
הטבילה. Beit HaTevilah. You go down, you go to the מקווה, mikvah,
you come up, you warm up. So pretty much every single designation
here is at contradiction. Okay? Every single one is different than the
one from... this so red, the so red is מדות, Middot, okay?
And black is תמיד. Tamid So some of them aren't a problem,
because some of them you could imagine had double usage. So the
fact that you had a fire here and you also... I'm sorry,
the fact that you,
the בית חשמונאים Beit Chashmonaim stored the אבני מזבח Mizbeach doesn't exactly
have to contradict with another use. So this isn't really considered to
be a contradiction. The fact that you would go to the בית
הטבילה Beit HaTevilah doesn't have to contradict with another use. But there
is a contradiction of where's the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and where's
the sheep? This says the sheep is here, this says it's here.
This says the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim is here, this says it's
here. Okay, so those two things are contradictory, okay? So even though,
again, you could just say, different authors, but we have two points
of contradiction: where is the sheep, and where is the לחם הפנים?
lechem hapanim, Okay. Now, what he is going to say is the
following: here's my solution. My solution is
that everybody really agrees that the sheep was not sort of somewhere
in the middle, and that we're just describing different ways where it
was, okay, whether you're saying southwest or northwest, it was really somewhere
in the middle. Okay, and that they're really describing the same room,
and it's just one is calling it northwest and one is calling
it southwest. That's the basic answer that we've given, right? But we're
saying that fundamentally
it is... ומסתברא דבמערב דרומי הוה, u-mistabra d'vi-ma'arav d'romi havah, it makes
more sense to say that it was in the southwest. Okay, that
it really is in
here, the southwest.
Why? If you say it's in the southwest, we're going to have
a way of solving this problem. What way are we going to
have of solving this problem? If it's in the southwest, and even
the one who calls it northwest really knows it's in the southwest,
then you can solve this contradiction of the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim
Why? Because what we're going to say is the following: that the
one who is listing the rooms here, the one in תמיד Tamid.
that is listing the rooms and going around, really for once is
not going counterclockwise, but is going clockwise. And that's going to solve
our problem. Because if you start here with the sheep, and you
assume it's in the southwest, we're going to reverse the order. The
northwest now will be the seals. Okay,
then this will be the בית המוקד. You see how I'm doing
it? I'm reversing the order rather than going around like this. And
then this will be the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim So we can
solve the contradiction of the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim if we reverse
the order that he's listing the rooms. He didn't tell us which
rooms he was talking about. He started with the one for the
sheep and then he listed the other three rooms, the author of
תמיד. So rather than assuming he's going counterclockwise, if we assume he's
going clockwise and we assume that even though he said that this
was a northwest room, he really knows it's southwest, then the לחם
הפניםs Lechem Hapanim will coincide. Is that more or less clear? Yes?
Sort of? Okay. All right. So he says that's how I know
that everybody really agrees that this is a southwest room. Let's read
that again. ומסתברא u-mistabra
it makes sense דבמערב דרומי הוה, d'vi-ma'arav d'romi havah, it really was
a southwest room. ממאי? דרמינן לחם הפנים אלחם הפנים, de-raminan lechem hapanim
a-lechem hapanim, there's a contradiction of which room was used for the
לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, for the baking of the bread. ומשנינן, and
the answer we give is, אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, מר
כחשיב דרך ימין, one is counting moving towards your right, which is
counterclockwise if you imagine yourself facing the center of the clock and
you move to your right, that's counterclockwise. ומר כחשיב דרך שמאל, the
other is going clockwise. אי אמרת בשלמא במערב דרומי הוה, i amrit
bishlama b'ma'arav d'romi havah, if it's in the southwest, היינו דמתרצת לחם
הפנים אלחם הפנים, hainu d'metartzat lechem hapanim a-lechem hapanim, then it all
works out. אלא אי אמרת צפונית מערבית הוה, ella i amrit tzfoni
ma'aravi havah, but if it really is in the northwest, and it
just can be described as southwest or northwest, סוף סוף מאי תירוצא
דלחם הפנים, sof sof mai tirutza de-lechem hapanim, what answer do you
have? אלא לאו שמע מינה במערב דרומי הוה, ella lav shema mina
b'ma'arav d'romi havah, שמע מינה. shema mina. So you see it's in
the southwest. Okay, so again, the one that listed the rooms of
the red actually labeled explicitly, if you looked at the original משנה,
and said the sheep was southwest, the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim it
said was southeast. So those rooms are not going to change. Those
were explicitly labeled. But the author of תמיד started with the sheep
and then just gave and then just listed the rooms, did not
tell you where they were located. So if we can make two
assumptions: that although he says sheep is northwest, it's really this middle
space room and he really admits it's southwest, and then he's going
around and he's going clockwise and not counterclockwise, the לחם הפניםs Lechem
HaPanim will coincide. coincide. But if he were to be going clockwise,
obviously they wouldn't coincide, לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim. would wind up here.
And if he were to be starting in the northwest, it wouldn't
coincide, it would all be off. The way you can get the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim. to coincide is to have him start in
the southwest and to be going clockwise. Okay, so that shows you
that that's his answer, that there really is not a contradiction. As
opposed to saying there's two authors, it's not a contradiction. This room
can be described both as northwest and southwest because it's somewhere between
the two. And the other contradictions can be reconciled by saying that
this author is going clockwise rather than counter-clockwise. שמע מינה. Shema Mina.
So I'm glad we got new markers for today. So said, so
בגמרא שמע
מינה. Bigemara Shema Mina. והא אמר, Veha Amar, how can you say
that the author of תמיד is going
clockwise? Don't we say כל פינות שאתה פונה לא יהו אלא דרך
ימין? Kol pinot sheata pone lo yehu ela derech yamin? Whenever you're
moving, you move to the right, למזרח, Lemizrach, to the east. I
mean, if that's when you're facing the altar, then the right is
your east. But anyway, what it means is you're always facing the
center and moving to your right, which means you're always moving counter-clockwise.
So the גמרא Gemara says הני מילי בעבודה. Hani mili beavoda.
Yeah, that's when you're actually doing the עבודה avoda in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash you're going up the ramp, so you move to
your right, not to your left. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, but here
we're just listing rooms. חושבנא בעלמא הוא, Hushbana bealma hu, we're just
listing rooms. So, he decided to list them in a clockwise direction,
not in a counter-clockwise direction. Okay, so that is our second answer.
Well, we had a third but we rejected it. So, we had
a problem here: תמיד listing of identifying which room is the sheep,
contradicting the משנה in מידות, Middot, and we have three answers. One
answer is that they're different authors, and the author of
מידות is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. We had
two reasons to say that. One is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov said, "Oh, I forgot what they used this room
for" in another משנה. The fact that he's bothering to say he
forgot sounds like he's the סתם stam voice, or else you don't
mention somebody who just forgot, what good is that? So that indicates
that the author of מידות is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov. And the other reason was because according to רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, it explained that whole discussion we
had yesterday about why you needed a low front wall of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash so the כהנים Kohanim who were slaughtering the
פרה אדומה Parah Adumah standing at Mount Olives could see through the
doorways into the door of the היכל. Heichal. That also fit with
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. So that was in
the סתם stam author of מידות, which is different than the סתם
stam author of תמיד.
Did I say that in the sense?
No, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov didn't say that.
The second answer was it was רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and he
needed the low wall because the מזבח was in the center. The
גמרא Gemara said that can't be correct because other indications of מידות
show that the מזבח was not in the center. So the only
answer so far, the one we started with today, is רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov is the author of מידות, and
that's why it feels like a contradiction of the rooms. And the
second answer is there is no contradiction of rooms. One says northwest,
one says southwest, they both agree the room was somewhat in the
middle. It was really a southwest room, but they were just describing
it differently. And the other contradictions can be reconciled by talking about
whether you're listing things clockwise or counter-clockwise. Okay, we now finally, thankfully,
get back to discussing the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Let's take a
look. Okay, so we mentioned the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol starts working
for the seven days before יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And it said
that in general, a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, those seven days he
was doing the עבודה avoda all by himself. But in general, a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can walk into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash.
any time and decide he's going to be מקריב makriv first. He's
going to do whatever קרבן korban he wants to be מקריב makriv
and he can take whatever portion of whatever קרבן korban he wants.
So, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, שכהן גדול מקריב חלק בראש, sheKohen Gadol
makriv chelek berosh, he gets first option at bringing any קרבן. korban.
ונוטל חלק בראש, Venoteil chelek berosh, he gets the first choice of
any of the divisions of the food of the קרבנות, korbanot, meat
or the bread and so on. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis
taught: כיצד מקריב חלק בראש? Keitzad makriv chelek berosh? What does this
mean he can offer up first?
Any day of the year.
Any day of the year, right. אומר עולה זו אני מקריב, Omer,
olah zu ani makriv, he goes and he says, "You know what?
I want to bring this קרבן עולה." korban olah. מנחה זו אני
מקריב, Mincha zu ani makriv, "I'd like to bring this מנחה." mincha.
You say, "Please, be my guest,
you're the כהן גדול." Kohen Gadol. Okay, כיצד נוטל חלק בראש? Keitzad
noteil chelek berosh? What does it mean he gets to take the
first portion of the division of the קרבן? korban?
אומר חטאת זו אני אוכל, Omer, chatat zu ani ocheil, "I'd like
to eat the meat from this חטאת." chatat. Okay, right. אשם זה
אני אוכל, Asham zeh ani ocheil, "Or I'd like to eat the
meat from this
אשם." asham. So he gets to eat it, "Please, take it." ונוטל
חלה משתי חלות, Venoteil challah mishtei challot, if you have the two
loaves that were brought on שבועות, Shavuot, he gets one of them.
Which the point here is now to set a little bit of
a limit, which means he doesn't take everything. He can't say "I'm
taking it all." He gets the first portion. How big is the
first portion? So we're going to see there's a debate whether the
first portion is up to fifty percent or has to be less
than fifty percent. He can get his first portion, but still, he's
one man, so maybe he has to always get a little bit
less than half. So the first position says he gets one of
the two חלות challot on שבועות Shavuot of לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim,
it sounds like he can get up to
fifty percent. And ארבע או... arba o... Yeah. Right. Exactly.
Well, he
can't eat the
עולה, Olah, that's why, so he was מקריב makriv the עולה, Olah,
he didn't eat it. Right. But any עולה, Olah, עולת נדבה olat
nedavah or קרבן ציבור korban tzibur as well presumably.
It could be an עולת תמיד. olat tamid.
Presumably anything. Right. רבי אומר, Rebbi Omer, so this is interesting that
when we get to לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim, where half would be
six, it says only four five. And רבי אומר, Rebbi Omer, רבי
Rebbi says לעולם חמש, le'olam chamesh, only five, or up to five,
not four five, five. שנאמר Shene'emar והיתה לאהרן ולבניו, vehayetah le'Aharon ulevanav,
it should be for Aaron and his sons, מחצה לאהרן ומחצה לבניו,
mechtzah le'Aharon umechtzah levanav, he's entitled up to half. Now, of course,
how five is half of 12 is not clear. Okay, so you
start by saying one of the two loaves of the שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem and then when you get to לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
where there are 12, you say four five and Rebbi says no,
no, no, half, five. So obviously that's going to be a little
bit of a problem. So let's take a look. הגופא קשיא. Ha
gufa kashya. This is itself a contradiction. אמרת Amart נותן לו אחת
משתי חלות. noten lo achat mishtei chalot.
First you say one out of two by the לחם הפנים. Lechem
Hapanim, מאן רבי היא? Man Rebbi hi? That must be Rebbi, דאמר
פלגא שקיל. de'amar palga shakil. He says half because the פסוק pasuk
of course at the end it says half. אימא מציעתא. Eima metzi'ata.
Then let's look at the next statement.
ארבע או חמש ממעשה לחם הפנים. Arba o chamesh mima'aseh Lechem HaPanim.
Four five from the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim. So that's not half.
אתאן לרבנן, Atan leRabbanan, דאמרי לא שקיל פלגא. de'amri lo shakil palga.
That's the Rabbis who says he has to get less than half.
אימא סיפא. Eima seifa. Let's look at the very end. רבי אומר
לעולם חמש. Rebbi omer le'olam chamesh. Rebbi says it's always five. Now
we're not yet dealing with the problem that five isn't half of
12, but what we are saying is it's clear that Rebbi means,
says half. Somehow five works out to be half of 12. We'll
get to that. So how do you deal with it? The first
one said one out of two loaves. That's the half position. Then
it says four five, that's obviously not the half position. Then you're
back to Rebbi, which is the half position. So what's it going
to be? רישא וסיפא רבי מציעתא רבנן? Reisha veseifa Rebbi metzi'ata Rabbanan?
The beginning and the end is Rebbi, the middle is the Rabbis?
That's crazy. It's bouncing back and forth. How do you make sense,
coherent sense, of this ברייתא? braita? So we're going to have two
answers. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says Abaye, רישא ומציעתא רבנן. Reisha umetzi'ata
Rabbanan. You know what? Yes, until you get to Rebbi's statement at
the end, it's all going like the Rabbis. So four five, less
than half of the 12 loaves, we get. Why do they say
one of the two loaves of שבועות? Shavuot? מודו רבנן בפרוסה דלאו
אורח ארעא למיתב לכהן גדול. Modu Rabbanan befrusah delav orach ar'a lemeiteiv
leKohen Gadol.
Because yes, he gets, he's supposed to get less than half, but
you don't give him a half a loaf, okay? So if you
have only two loaves, you round up and he gets a full
loaf. He's not going to get point nine of a loaf. So
basically the first two positions are the רבנן. Rabbanan. The Rabbis say
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can get his first portion, but it
has to be less than half, but if there's only two, he's
going to get one. Okay? He's not going to get less than
one. That's the Rabbis. And then Rebbi says no, no, no, it's
always half. How five is half, we'll worry about, but the first
point before we get to that is that the first two positions
before Rebbi's introduced is basically that of the רבנן, Rabbanan, less than
half with the qualification that you round to the nearest unit.
Now, yes, it's interesting, there is a דעה de'ah that a פרוסה
frusah can serve as לחם משנה lechem mishneh for שבת. Shabbat.
Yeah, yeah, not only that, but the כהנים kohanim divided the לחם
הפנים, Lechem HaPanim they got a פרוסה. frusah. Like there's even a
famous גמרא Gemara in the beginning of פסחים Pesachim that a כהן
kohen was complaining that he got such a small piece of the
bread and so on. Okay, but this is the כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, for his כבוד kavod you give him a whole one. Okay,
ומאי ארבע או חמש לרבנן? Umai arba o chamesh leRabbanan? Now, if
we say the first two, so when it says one, it really
is the Rabbis less than half but we round, we give him
a whole, one. Now four five. Now why four five? Okay, we,
you know, again, why mention specifically four five? If it's less than
six, just say, you know, five, or whatever. What's the point of
saying four five? How would that play out?
So
there's a debate how the כהנים kohanim would normally divide
the bread when they, you know, on שבת. Shabbat. Forget כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. There would be, שבת Shabbat would be the changing of
the guards. You'd have the new משמר, mishmar, new group of כהנים
kohanim would come in on שבת, Shabbat, the old would leave. And
you've got 12 loaves. So logically you would say 12 loaves, you
have both כהנים kohanim serving on שבת, Shabbat, you basically, you know,
both groups, one leaving, one coming, you would divide it six and
six. That's one position. That's the position of the רבנן. Rabbanan. There's
a position of a different רבנן. Rabbanan. There's a debate of רבנן
Rabbanan and רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. There's a position of רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda that actually it would be five and five and the
extra two would go to the new guys. Why would the new
guys get, I mean, it would wind up to be seven and
five? But conceptually you'd set aside two, that would be a special
gift to the new guys. And then you'd be left with 10
and you divide it five and five. Why would the new guys
get two? Because they had to do the clean up job, the
wrap up job of the old guys. The old guys opened the
gates and the new guys when the day began, and the new
guys came in and they closed the gates. So they get extra
payment. You're closing the gates that we opened. It's quite fascinating just
to think about it because of course they're going to get, it's
going to be the reverse by next שבת, Shabbat, right? They're going
to open the gates and some new group is going to close
it. But it does speak to like psychologically the idea, you know,
you made the mess and I have to clean it, it doesn't
matter if next
time... Right now I'm cleaning up your mess. It doesn't feel so
fair. So we gave the new guy, not like a mess, but
we gave the new guy two loaves to close the gate at
the end of the day that the old guys opened. So according
to the רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the division was seven and five,
but conceptually two were seen as a special set aside designated gift
or payment to the new guys and the real stuff up for
division was the remaining ten which they divided five and five. And
this is now how it's going to work out the two numbers
of five or four according to the Rabbis that he gets less
than half. Let's see how it plays out.
לרבנן דאמרי Lerabanan de'amri going to the Rabbis that say over there
in סוכה, Sukkah, נכנס נוטל שש nichnas notel shesh ויוצא נוטל שש,
veyotzei notel shesh, the new group gets six and the
old group, those coming in get six and those leaving get six.
ושכר הגפת דלתות לא, uschar hagafat delatos lo, משתים עשרה לא, mishteim
asrei lo, and there's no
payment for closing the gates. There's no special payment for closing the
gates for the new guys. So משתים עשרה בעי מיפלג. mishteim asrei
ba'i miflag. Okay, so you have to divide from twelve. בציר חד
מפלגא חמש. batzir chad mipahlga chamesh. So remember the Rabbis say that
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has to get less than half. So
twelve is the amount that's divided, no special payment for closing the
gates. So half of twelve is six, one less than six is
five. So that's חמש שקיל. chamesh shakil. So he gets five. Okay,
so the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol gets five. Five is one less
than half. That's the Rabbis that say you get less than half.
The group of guys in the משמר. mishmar. It's a משמר. mishmar.
It's all of the כהנים Kohanim that would serve that week. It's
a lot. Okay, לרבי יהודה דאמר leRav Yehuda de'amar נכנס נוטל שבע,
nichnas notel sheva, so according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says
the new group gets seven, שתים בשכר הגפת דלתות, shtayim bischar hagafat
delatos, two for closing the gates, ויוצא נוטל חמש, veyotzei notel chamesh,
and the new group gets and the old group, the group leaving
gets five. So מעשר בעי מיפלג. me'eser ba'i miflag. So basically the
amount up for division, two is designated, is set aside. So the
amount of the bread that's up to be divided amongst the כהנים
Kohanim is ten. מיפלג, miflag, מעשר
בעי מיפלג. me'eser ba'i miflag. You got to divide ten. בציר חד
מפלגא, batzir chad mipahlga, one less than half, take away one from
half, ושקיל ארבע ve-shakil arba, and he gets four. Okay, so according
to the Rabbis that say the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol gets less
than half unless it's not a whole unit. So by the שתי
הלחם Shtei Halechem on שבועות Shavuot he gets one because you have
to round up to the unit. By the לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim
one less than half, so if you assume half is six, that
means five. If you assume half is five because two were set
aside, then one less than half is four. So that's why it
says five or four. Okay, and then רבי Rabbi comes along and
רבי Rabbi says no, no, no, it's always going to be five
and we'll see how that makes sense in a minute. Yeah.
If the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol walks in on this particular שבת,
Shabbos, there's one loaf leftover for the whole group?
Not one. What do you mean one? He
takes, no, no, no, he doesn't take it all from one group.
He takes חלק בראש chelek berosh before it gets divided. Here are
ten loaves to be divided. I'll take four. You guys divide the
remaining six. Or here are twelve loaves to be divided. I'll take
five. You guys divide the remaining
seven.
So he walks in, there's significantly less for everyone else.
They're all hoping he's not exactly.
It's good to be כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, now, that's how אביי Abaye reads the
משנה until you get to רבי Rabbi at the end. We don't
know why רבי Rabbi five is half. We'll worry about that in
a minute. But the first position is דרבנן, DeRabbanan, less than half.
Less than half of twelve will either be five or four depending
on if you're starting with twelve or ten. Okay, רבא אמר כולה
רבי היא. Rava amar kula Rabbi hi. It's all רבי. Rabbi. The
whole thing is all assuming exactly half. So now, so that's why
we understand the first opinion that says of the שתי הלחם Shtei
Halechem on שבועות Shavuot he gets one. That's half. How are we
going to deal with four and five? How's four and five going
to be half of twelve? Doesn't he
take
from the five loaves? No, the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim was קדשי
קדשים. kodshei kodshim. It had to be eaten in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash Okay, most of this stuff had to be eaten right
there in the עזרה. azara. He himself. Yeah, the only thing not
is the pieces of the שלמים shelamim which is not a full
קרבן. korban. Most of the stuff had to be eaten right there
in the עזרה. azara. Okay, so now how is four and five
according to רבי Rabbi going to be half of twelve? Let's take
a look.
וסבר לה כרבי יהודה. Vesavar lah keRav Yehuda. Now he holds like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says that two were set aside. If
two were set aside you're left with ten. So we get how
five is half. Right? You're with me here? Right? You have ten
of the לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim two are set aside, so five
is half. How does four get to be half? וסבר לה כרבי
יהודה ואלא מאי ארבע? Vesavar lah keRav Yehuda ve'ella mai arba? So
what does four mean? What does it mean five or four? הכא
חמש בעי למשקל? Hachamesh ba'i lishkol? He should take five because if
even if you assume like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that you're left
with ten, you should take
five. So לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דאיכא משמר
המתעכב הא דליכא משמר המתעכב. Ha de'ika mishmar hamit'akev ha deleika mishmar
hamit'akev. The question is, is there a משמר mishmar that is staying
behind? What does that mean? It means... It is the following: it
means on a שבת, Shabbos, you had two groups of כהנים Kohanim
serving at the same time, and that's why they would divide it
six and six or five and five or whatever. לא. Lo. Let's
say it was a יום טוב. Yom Tov. On a יום טוב,
Yom Tov, everybody was supposed to be עולה לרגל, oleh l'regel, so
all the כהנים Kohanim were also עולה לרגל. oleh l'regel. So all
the כהנים Kohanim would do the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash, on a יום טוב, Yom Tov, and they would all
divide equally. Now, let's say it happens to be a יום טוב
Yom Tov on שבת. Shabbos. So you had all the כהנים Kohanim
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash all 24 groups of כהנים, Kohanim,
you'd have to divide the 12 loaves of bread amongst 24 groups,
not just two groups, okay? Let's say, however, it was a יום
טוב Yom Tov that was right before שבת. Shabbos.
Meaning, שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov were juxtaposed. יום טוב
Yom Tov was either on Friday, or יום טוב Yom Tov was
on Sunday, okay? And שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov were
juxtaposed. So all the כהנים Kohanim had to be there for שבת,
Shabbos, they had to come up for יום טוב Yom Tov for
the רגל, regel, so they had no choice, they had to be
there for שבת. Shabbos. So the שבת Shabbos right before or right
after יום טוב Yom Tov was like a שבת Shabbos on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. All the כהנים Kohanim would do the עבודה, avodah,
they would all divide it equally. What about if there was like
a Thanksgiving Day weekend? Which is,
technically Thanksgiving is only Thursday, but we know everybody takes off Friday
as well. You're lucky they don't also take off Wednesday and then
Tuesday. Okay, so let's say יום טוב Yom Tov was on a,
יום טוב Yom Tov was not on a Friday, יום טוב Yom
Tov was on a Thursday, okay? So everybody was עולה לרגל oleh
l'regel for יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now, technically, you can go home
on a Friday, okay? But who really wants to start going home
on a Friday from ירושלים? Yerushalayim? So you're going to stay over
and you're going to stay through שבת. Shabbos. Okay, that's מתעכב. mitakev.
You could go home, but you stayed the extra day, and therefore
there might be extra כהנים Kohanim around on this שבת Shabbos that
are held over from the יום טוב. Yom Tov. Or reverse would
be, like the, to use the other להבדיל lehavdil analogy, President's weekend,
Monday, you're off Monday. So you're off Monday, well, maybe that's not
such a good analogy. But anyway, who, so if Monday is יום
טוב, Yom Tov, who wants to, you know, what, you want to
travel on Sunday? No, you'll come up to ירושלים Yerushalayim on ערב
שבת erev Shabbos and you'll stay through שבת, Shabbos, Sunday, and then
Monday you'll be there for יום טוב. Yom Tov. So these are
scenarios in which שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov are juxtaposed,
but there's a day between them, where technically you could go home,
but there's a lot of impetus, you know, to want to stay.
In those cases, if you happen to stay there for that שבת
Shabbos and you're, and it's not your שבת, Shabbos, but you're there
because of יום טוב, Yom Tov, and you're there and you could,
you don't have to be there but you are there, you serve
in the בית המקדש and you are entitled to a portion of
the קרבנות, korbanot, but not an equal portion. Because again, it's not
like you're forced to be here, you're choosing to be here, we
understand why, but you're not forced. If it were סתם stam a
normal random שבת Shabbos of the year, go home, come back on
your day. But this day, you're allowed to be there, but you
don't get an equal portion. So how much do you get? So
all the כהנים Kohanim that are visiting and are with us this
שבת, Shabbos, even though they don't have to be here, all of
them get two of the, two of the 12 loaves of the
לחם lechem. הפנים. And the כהנים Kohanim that are supposed to be
here this שבת, Shabbos, those two groups, they divide the remaining 10,
okay? So that's basically the story. If you have people that are
holding over, you know, came early or staying a little late, you
have two fewer loaves of לחם הפנים for the כהנים Kohanim that
are supposed to be here. So
if we're assuming like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you would always set
aside two for the כהנים Kohanim that were coming in, and it's
one of those יום טוב Yom Tov שבתes Shabbos where you have
extra כהנים Kohanim here, where, you know, they don't have to be
here but they came an extra day early or whatever, you give
all the extra כהנים Kohanim two. So two to the כהנים Kohanim
that are coming in, two to the extra כהנים, Kohanim, and you
have eight that are left for dividing. So if there are eight
left for dividing, half of that would be four. Okay, so what
רבא Rava says is, even the position of four and five can
work with the idea that they get half. א, Alef, you assume
like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so you always really just start with
10, not 12, that gets you five. And under some scenarios, you're
going to have two fewer, one of those יום טוב Yom Tov
שבת Shabbos scenarios and you'll have eight, and half of that will
get you four. Okay, so, so החמש באו מן השלישי, hachamesh ba'u
min hashelishi, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דאיכא משמר
המתעכב, ha de-ika mishmar ha-mitakev, הא דליכא משמר
המתעכב. ha de-leika mishmar ha-mitakev. If there's an extra group that's hanging
back, then, then they get, then
that extra group gets two and you're down to שמונה shmoneh to
divide. If there's no extra group hanging back, or it's not a
יום טוב Yom Tov שבת Shabbos scenario, then there is עשר. eser.
אי איכא משמר המתעכב משמונה בעי למפלג. ei ika mishmar ha-mitakev mishmoneh
ba'i le-miflag. If there's a משמר mishmar hanging back because of a
יום טוב Yom Tov שבת Shabbos scenario, then two for the כהנים
Kohanim coming in, two extra, two for those כהנים Kohanim that are
hanging back, you have שמונה shmoneh left, ושקיל veshakil ארבע, arba and
he gets four. אי ליכא משמר המתעכב מעשר בעי למפלג, ei leika
mishmar ha-mitakev me-eser ba'i le-miflag, and if there isn't that scenario, then
there's עשר. eser. Two are for the extra כהנים Kohanim for coming
in, basically 10 of the loaves, so חמש בעי למפלג ושקיל חמש,
chamesh ba'i le-miflag ve-shakil chamesh, he gets half, it's five. אי הכי
מאי רבי אומר לעולם חמש? ei hachi mai Rabbi omer l'olam chamesh?
So if the whole thing is רבי, Rabbi, again, think about what
the ברייתא braita said. First it said of the two loaves on
שבועות Shavuos he gets one, okay, so that's רבי Rabbi half. This
is what רבא Rava is saying, it's all רבי, Rabbi, he says
half. Then it said, and of the לחם. לחם הפנים four five.
Why? Because according to רבי, Rebbi, the לחם הפנים after you give
out the special amount, you're either down to 10 or down to
eight, so it's going to be four five. That works even if
you say half. But the last line that says רבי Rebbi says
you always get half, you always get five, because it says אהרן
Aharon and his kids and they always divide half and half. So
if רבי Rebbi just got through saying four five, why here is
he saying oh it's always five? It sounds like clearly the line
that came before him was not רבי. Rebbi. So the גמרא Gemara
says okay קשיא kashya fine, maybe רבי, Rebbi, maybe it's רבי Rebbi
and he's just saying on a normal basis it's always five. Anyway,
this is one read that it's all רבי. Rebbi. The simpler read
of course is that until you get to that last line it's
not רבי Rebbi and that's אביי's Abaye read. That the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol gets less than half. If there's only two loaves he
gets one because you have to give him a whole.
If it's a normal if by the לחם הפנים where you start
with 12, four five is going to be one less than half.
Half will be six or five based on whether you say the
you set aside two loaves. So that'll be six or five. And
then רבי Rebbi says, that'll be four five. And then רבי Rebbi
says it'll always be five because רבי Rebbi says half, but presumably
he would also say two loaves always get set aside. So if
two loaves always get set aside it has to be always five
because he says always half. Bottom line is there's the debate whether
when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol gets the first, gets the rights
to the first portion, does it have to be at least a
little bit less than half or can or is it always a
full half debate of the רבי Rebbi and חכמים. Chachamim. To be
continued tomorrow.
How large is the roast?